Maddy: Communication is a key component
for any workplace, no matter what the
industry is, or the line of work involves.
But for communication to be effective,
everyone should know what and how they’re
expected to communicate with each other
and who they should be reporting to.
Phillip: Everyone should know what their
responsibilities are, or work will stop, timelines
will be crashed, and goals won’t be achieved, as
people won’t know what they’re meant to be doing!
Maddy: Effective communication
boosts productivity.
When people are communicating, they’re
coordinating and they’re cooperating,
meaning it’s much more likely that work is
being done on time to the right standard.
People will feel more connected with both
their colleagues and their organisation, making
them happier and more focused on their work,
therefore improving productivity and efficiency.
Without effective communication people will
feel disconnected from each other, even if they
know what their responsibilities and duties are.
Phillip: Effective communication drives
engagement A business where people are
being effectively communicated with about
their responsibilities and priorities is
one that is probably hitting its targets.
But if efforts aren’t made to make
employees feel engaged, this will
only last a certain amount of time.
By effectively communicating things like the
business’s purpose and ambitions, sharing
success stories, and encouraging social
communication, employees will feel more like
they’re part of something bigger than themselves.
Maddy: Effective communication encourages
loyalty, and it means that if information about
the business and career possibilities within
the organisation, is being spread, people will
be more likely to want to stay for longer.
By encouraging loyalty and employee retention
a company can avoid potentially expensive
and disruptive searches for new employees.
Let’s consider for example that a company
has internal fast tracks to promote promising
employees to management positions, but it doesn’t
communicate this fact about itself to its people.
They then won’t know that’s an option, so
they might look for opportunities elsewhere.
But, if its existence is made clear
through effective communication, their
retention of talented staff should improve.
Phillip: Effective communication
creates a health ideas ecosystem.
If people and teams are able to easily
share their experiences, knowledge, and
ideas, that means there is a constant
information flow in the business.
This is fertile soil for the growth of
novel ideas and approaches, helping the
business stay competitive and efficient.
Maddy: Effective communication
helps with employee wellbeing.
When people feel engaged and know
they’re being heard by their colleagues,
this is positive for their wellbeing.
No one likes to feel on their own or unheard.
Effective communication is a powerful tool
to resist that feeling, especially important
given how many people now work remotely.
Phillip: Imagine for example, a company
that has a lot of remote workers, a
model adopted during the pandemic.
This has continued as it offers a lot of
benefits, meaning they can hire talent
from a much wider geographic range.
But they’ve noticed that some employees are
talking about feeling isolated and lonely.
So, a dedicated social channel is set up
on the company’s internal instant messaging
platform to encourage people to have those
casual “get to know you” conversations
that would happen naturally in an office.
This helps people feel less lonely
and improves employee wellbeing.
Maddy: We can see that there are many ways that
effective communication is of great importance
to a business and that it is essential for
building and managing working relationships.
Without it, organisations, and employees within
them will struggle to reach their full potential.
We can also see that effective communication
impacts a business at all levels, helping with
decision making, encouraging innovation, and
keeping a business competitive, alongside helping
to maintain a productive and engaged workforce.